<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Cluedo>
  <graphic url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Cluedo_1956_Small_Red_Box_Edition.jpg"/>
  <note>Cluedo 1956 UK Edition depicting a Sherlock Holmes type character.</note>
  <note>Depending on edition, the playing pieces are typically made of coloured plastic, shaped
        like chess pawns, or character figurines. Occasionally they are made from wood or pewter.
        The standard edition of Cluedo comes with six basic tokens representing the following
        original characters:</note>
  <Suspects>
    <suspect>
      <person>Miss Scarlett</person>
      <note>(spelt <alias>Miss Scarlet</alias> in North American versions after 1963 &#x2013; a red
                piece)</note>
    </suspect>
    <suspect>
      <person>Colonel Mustard</person>
      <note>(a yellow piece)</note>
    </suspect>
    <suspect>
      <person>Mrs. White</person>
      <note>(a white piece)</note>
    </suspect>
    <suspect>
      <person>Reverend Green</person>
      <note>(named <alias>Mr. Green</alias> in pre-2002 North American versions &#x2013; a green
                piece)</note>
    </suspect>
    <suspect>
      <person>Mrs. Peacock</person>
      <note>(a blue piece)</note>
    </suspect>
    <suspect>
      <person>Professor Plum</person>
      <note>(a purple piece)</note>
    </suspect>
  </Suspects>
  <Victims>
    <victim><note>in North American versions</note><person>Dr. Black</person>, <note>in the UK version</note><alias>Mr. Boddy</alias></victim>
  </Victims>
  <Weapons>
    <note>The current standard set of North American &amp; UK miniature weapons tokens </note>
    <note>The traditional UK 2nd edition gold-tone miniature weapons tokens (note the gun is an
            updated <weapon><object>Walther PP</object></weapon>) The playing tokens are typically made out of unfinished <material>pewter</material>, with
            the exception of the Rope, which may also come in <material>plastic</material> or <material>string</material> depending on
            edition. Special editions have included <material>gold</material> plated, <material>brass</material> finished and <material>Sterling silver</material>
            versions, which have appeared in a variety of designs. </note>
    <weapon>
      <object>Candlestick</object>
    </weapon>
    <weapon>
      <object>Dagger</object>
      <note>(A <alias>Knife</alias> in North American editions, each
                represented by a respective depiction)</note>
    </weapon>
    <weapon>
      <object>Lead Pipe</object>
      <note>(called Lead Piping in earlier UK editions, the early tokens were made out of
                actual <material>lead</material> and therefore pose a risk of lead poisoning)</note>
    </weapon>
    <weapon>
      <object>Revolver</object>
    </weapon>
    <note>(first depicted in the UK as a Dreyse M1907 semi-automatic pistol,[7] and in North
            America as a Colt M1911 pistol. All current editions typically represent an Allan &amp;
            Thurber Pepper-box revolver first depicted in the 1972 Clue edition)</note>
    <weapon>
      <object>Rope</object>
      <note>(originally represented by a natural fibre coiled piece of string, the standard
                edition now consists of <material>molded plastic</material> or metal)</note>
    </weapon>
    <weapon>
      <object>Spanner</object>
      <note>(called <alias>Wrench</alias> in North American editions and
                depicted as a <alias>Monkey wrench</alias>, it may also be shown as an <alias>Open-ended spanner</alias> in some
                traditional UK versions)</note>
    </weapon>
  </Weapons>
  <Rooms>
    <floor>
      <note>There are nine rooms in the mansion where the murder can take place, laid out in a
            circular fashion on the game board, separated by pathways overlaid by playing spaces.
            Each of the four corner rooms contains a secret passage that leads to the room on the
            opposite diagonal corner of the map. The center room (often referred to as the
                <room>Cellar</room>, or <room>Stairs</room>) is inaccessible to the players, but
            contains the <mcguffin>solution envelope</mcguffin>, and is not otherwise used during
            game play. Coloured "start" spaces encircle the outer perimeter which correspond to each
            player's person token. Each character starts at the corresponding colored space.</note>
      <room>Ballroom</room>
      <room>Kitchen</room>
      <room>Conservatory</room>
      <room>Dining Room</room>
      <room>Cellar</room>
      <room>Billiard Room</room>
      <room>Library</room>
      <room>Hall</room>
      <room>Lounge</room>
      <room>Study</room>
      <note>there are secret passages to opposite corners.</note>
    </floor>
  </Rooms>
</Cluedo>
